なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜兄とは常に➡
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
弟の先を
行ってなければならない＞
ひびと
おれ
(南波日々人)⦅ムッちゃん 俺
今 なんとなく➡
Mu, I really think...
なんとなく 将来は
宇宙飛行士になってさ➡
I really think I want to become an astronaut.
I believe I can make it to the moon.
月に行くような気がしたよ⦆
⦅俺らは２人で
宇宙飛行士になるぞ⦆
⦅うん⦆
The two of us will become astronauts.
＜あれから…＞
It's been twenty years since we made that promise on the hill.
＜あの高台での約束から２０年＞
⦅イエ～！⦆
Yay!
＜日々人がついに…➡
Hibito has finally
月から帰ってきた＞
returned from the moon!
た～いま｡
Good to be back.
ねぇ 何それ？ねぇ 何それ？
Hey, what's that?
What is it?
日々人 これって…｡
Hibito, is this...
月の石に決まってんじゃん｡
オミヤゲ｡
A moon rock, of course.
It's a souvenir.
Seriously? Wow!
え マジで!?
《スゲ～！》
つき
ヘェ～！これが月の
ムーンの ストーンなの！
So this is a stone from the moon?
(南波父)普通だな｡
Looks normal.
お前という奴は…
こんな貴重なものを➡
I can't believe you just tossed it like you would any other normal rock!
そこらへんの石みたいに
投げやがって｡
ムッちゃんも行くんだろ 月｡
Aren't you going to the moon?
月で見たら
そこらへんの石だったよ｡
Once you're there, you can find these anywhere.
《チクショー!!》
Argh!
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#62 Those Who Dream Far
(アラン)パパー！パパー！➡
Daddy! Daddy!
おかえり パパー！
Welcome back, Daddy!
(ダミアン)ただいま！アラン！
I'm back, Alan!
けいかい
そう警戒するなよ｡
息子にはちゃんと伝えてあるよ｡➡
Don't be so paranoid.
I told my son he has to stay at a distance.
近づいちゃダメだって｡➡
ごめんな アラン｡一緒に遊べる
のは もう少し先なんだ｡
Sorry, Alan...
It'll be a little longer before I can play with you.
うん！わかってるよ｡
Yep, I know!
３人とも！そろそろ出発だぞ～｡
Hey! We should get going!
じゃあ 行ってくる｡
これからすぐ ﾒﾃﾞｨｶﾙﾁｪｯｸなんだ｡
I've gotta head off...
They need to give us medical checkups.
Such a pain.
めんどくせ～だろ？
明日には帰るよ｡
I'll be back in the morning.
Okay.
さあもう大丈夫だ｡
みんな横になっていいぞ｡
Now, everything will be fine...
You can lie down.
想像以上だね｡
からだ
カゼひいたみたいに体 重いや｡
This is worse than I expected...
My body's sluggish, like when I have a cold.
立ってるのも
かなりキツかったな｡➡
I could barely stand upright.
足がガタついてたの
バレなかったかな｡
Wonder if anyone knew...
えがお
(リンダ)私も…相当 笑顔
引きつってたかも｡
Same here.
My smile was probably a bit strained.
３人とも堂々としてたよ｡
さすが 選ばれし宇宙飛行士だ｡
You all looked strong from here.
That's why you were chosen as astronauts.
そうそう！月と比べりゃ
服も体も 重さ６倍よ｡➡
Exactly.
On Earth, your body and clothes weigh six times as much.
あれだけの余裕を見せられる
なんて 本当に大したもんよね｡
It takes a lot to act normal under those circumstances.
子供に飛びつかれただけで
にくばな
肉離れを起こす…か｡➡
You could suffer a serious muscle injury if a child tackled you.
As a father, being unable to hold my son
帰ってすぐ自分の子供を
抱き上げられないってのは➡
父親として頼りなさ
この上なし だな｡
the moment I returned makes me feel bad.
Everyone feels that way.
みんなそうだよ｡
きかん
地上への帰還で 一番怖いのは➡
In fact, children are the most dangerous thing an astronaut faces upon return.
実は 子供なのよね｡
さて…｡これから４５日間に及ぶ
リハビリに入るわけだけど➡
Well, then...
You'll undergo rehab over the next forty-five days.
地球の重力になれるまでは➡
In the first few days, you'll likely experience extreme fatigue.
ねむけ
数日間 ひどい眠気に
おそわれると思うわ｡➡
リハビリ期間中の仕事は
基本 １日３時間まで｡
During your rehab, you'll work for three hours a day.
(ｵﾘﾋﾞｱ)寝て検査して運動して
また寝て…と➡
Sleep, run tests, exercise, then more sleep...
そういうサイクルが この先…｡
That will be your cycle.
Indeed, you will be extremely fatigued.
ひどい眠気におそわれるからね｡
⦅ねぇ ヒビト 覚えておいて⦆
Say, Hibito...
Remember this.
⦅は？何を？⦆
Huh? Remember what?
⦅あなたには お兄ちゃんを
引っ張っていく程の力がある⦆
You have the strength to lead your brother.
⦅あなたがいつも
ムッタの前にいて➡
If you stay ahead of Mutta and lead the way,
先に進み続けていれば…➡
Mutta will be right behind you.
ムッタは あなたに
引っ張られて前進できるわ⦆
⦅もしも あなたが
止まってしまったら➡
If you ever stop,
その時はきっと…
後ろからムッタが➡
I'm certain
Mutta will give you a push from behind.
あなたの背中を押してくれる｡➡
あなた達は きっと
そんな素敵な兄弟になる⦆
That's the wonderful relationship
that you brothers share.
Are you awake, Hibito?
お目覚めかい？ 日々人？
いい夢みたか？ ハハ｡
Have a good dream?
Yeah...
Sorry for the rush, but I'm going to begin your checkup.
さっそくで悪いが
ﾒﾃﾞｨｶﾙﾁｪｯｸを始めるぞ｡
オッケイ｡
Okay.
《いやぁ～…➡
走ってる女性って
やっぱ いいよね～》
A woman running really is a fine thing...
For some reason, I don't feel tired at all.
《なぜだろう…全然疲れない》
《前よりも…強く感じる…｡➡
My premonition is growing stronger...
Should I tell him?
《ちゃんと話すべきか…➡
だま
黙っておくべきか…》
Or should I keep quiet?
《いや…私は きっと話す》
No, I must tell him.
Hibito, want okayu porridge for dinner?
(母)日々人～ 晩ごはん
おかゆにしようか おかゆ｡
いや 別にカゼひいてるわけじゃ
ないから｡体が重いだけで…｡
No, I'm not sick or anything.
I just feel sluggish.
それより アポのけてくんない？
Anyway, could you move Apo?
アポも重さ６倍なんだよ｡
He's six times heavier now.
ワン ワン ワン！
うどんでいいんじゃないか？
Udon should be fine.
それもそうね｡
ちょっと…｡
I guess.
Wait...
Then, we'll have udon, Hibito...
というわけで うどんにするわね
日々人｡フニャフニュの うどん｡
Soggy udon.
普通のにして｡
Normal udon is fine.
Normal soggy udon.
(母)≪普通のフニャフニャね≫
(父)≪フニャフニャ
それもまた うどん≫
Soggy udon is still udon.
《父ちゃんも元気だし
母ちゃんも 超元気…➡
Dad is healthy, and Mom is super healthy.
じゃあ 一体…》
So, then...
《どういうことだ!?アマンティ》
What did you mean, Amanti?
(アマンティ)あのね…➡
You know...
When we first met, I could see into your future.
ムッタに初めて会ったあの時
少しだけ未来の様子が見えたの｡
ムッタも感付いてたんでしょう？
私が何か見たって｡
You probably noticed that I'd seen something.
えっ あ ああ…まあね｡
Huh? Ah, yeah...
《えっ あれって…熱が
出るってことじゃなかったの!?》
Eh? Hold on.
Wasn't my fever the bad news she foresaw?
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)日を重ねるごとに
だんだんはっきり見えて➡
Each day, my vision grows clearer, so I decided to talk to you.
話すことにしたの｡
私が見たのは…
ムッタがとても悲しんで➡
I saw you
looking pained and very sad.
つら
辛い思いをしている姿｡➡
ムッタに直接
何かが起こるわけじゃないの｡➡
Nothing bad will happen to you directly,
but to someone you know very well...
ムッタのよく知る誰か…➡
誰かが近いうちに重い病気になる｡
Someone will soon be stricken by serious illness.
Is it Hibito?
まさか…日々人が？
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)それは たぶん違う｡➡
Probably not.
帰ってきた日々人を見て
わかったの｡
When I saw his return, I knew...
日々人もあなたと同じように
辛い思いをすると思う｡
He's going to suffer just as much as you are.
現在
《誰かが…病気に？》
Someone will
get sick?
かんりかん
(管理官)入国の目的は？
ビジネス？観光？
What is the purpose of your visit?
Business or pleasure?
ビジネスです｡
どこへ？職種は？
Business.
Where are you headed? What line of work?
天文学者です｡
ゴダード飛行研究所で➡
I'm an astronomer.
I'm going to a Goddard Space Flight Center conference on the lunar observatory.
月面天文台建設の計画会議を｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)お待たせ みんな｡
Sorry to keep everyone waiting.
厳しいもんですね～ 入国って｡
It takes time to get through customs.
ホントよね｡
私なんて母国なのに｡
It does, and I was even born here.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ゴダードでの
プレゼンが終わったら➡
Once the Goddard presentation is done, we should head over to Houston.
みんなで
ヒューストンに行きましょう｡
会いたい宇宙飛行士が
２人もいるの｡
There are two astronauts I'm dying to see.
Thus, the ideal location would be on the moon's far side or within a crater.
かんそく
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)よって 観測地点は
月の裏側か➡
クレーター内部が
てき
適していると思われます｡➡
月面基地のあるシｬクルトン付近の
ちゅうふく
クレーター中腹｡➡
At the moment, we have selected Shackleton crater for the construction site.
けんぞう
そこを 建造予定地と
考えています｡
ゆうりょくし
我々が今 有力視しているのは
月面…電波望遠鏡です｡
The most probable scenario on the moon would be a radio telescope.
(天文学者)電波って…
ぶんかいのう
分解能が低いでしょ｡
Radio telescopes tend to provide images that aren't very clear.
光学望遠鏡にした方が
いいんじゃない？
Wouldn't an optical telescope be better?
That won't work.
そりゃ 無理だ｡
直径５ｍの光学望遠レンズを➡
Think of the cost to send an optical lens with a diameter of fifty-five meters there.
月まで送るコストを考えてみろ｡
ばくだい
莫大だぞ｡
A fortune!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ウホンッ｡
あ はい…｡
クチにチャック｡
Oh, yes...
Zip it.
One of the questions is how the radio telescope would be constructed.
気になることの１つは➡
どうやって この電波望遠鏡を
造るかだと思います｡➡
ていあん
我々の提案する方法では
少量のカーボンナノチューブと➡
We propose to transport a small quantity of carbon nanotubes and epoxy resin to the moon.
じゅし
エポキシ樹脂を月に送ります｡➡
これに 月のダストを混ぜて
はんしゃきょう
反射鏡のﾕﾆｯﾄを複数作ります｡➡
These materials can be mixed with lunar dust to create multiple reflecting mirrors.
このユニットをつなぎ合わせて➡
We will then connect the mirrors to build the giant radio telescope.
巨大な電波望遠鏡を
製作するのです｡➡
この方法なら
プエルトリコにある➡
With this method, we can construct a telescope the size of Puerto Rico's Arecibo Observatory.
アレシボ電波望遠鏡レベルの物も
製作可能です｡
つまり この案は 月に望遠鏡を
送り込むのではなく➡
In other words, we do not propose to transport a telescope to the moon.
月で望遠鏡を造ってしまう
というわけです｡
Our proposal is to construct the telescope there.
(ﾓﾘｿﾝ)ふん…｡
《なるほど｡これが実現すれば
素ン晴らしいね》
I see.
If it comes to fruition, this project would be wonderful...
月で造ってしまう…
って 誰がです？
Construct the telescope on the moon?
Who would do it?
そりゃ ロボットでしょ｡
They'd use robots.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)もちろん 多くをロボットに
頼ると思いますが➡
Naturally, we would primarily rely on robots,
but we would also need humans nearby.
人の手も必要に
なってくるでしょう｡
ナサ
そこで ＮＡＳＡの宇宙飛行士に
いらい
協力を依頼します｡
Which is why we will be soliciting NASA for astronaut assistance.
ごうりてき
(天文学者)合理的でないな｡
How do you rationalize that decision?
If we have to send people, you'll exceed our budget.
人を月に送る時点で
予算オーバーというもんだ｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)当然 予算は最低限に
おさえる必要があります｡➡
I understand that funding is a serious concern,
ですから 皆さんと一緒に…｡
but if we all work together—
なんにしても莫大すぎますよ｡
計画も資金も…｡
The scope and required funding are too great.
I'm not confident about the project's size.
恐ろしくて 手が出せませんよ｡
フゥ…｡
スゥーッ｡
皆さん！予算のことを考える前に
一度 想像してみてください！➡
Everyone, before you consider funding,
I'd like you to use your imaginations.
空気のゆらぎのない
とら
月面から捉えた 澄んだ宇宙を！➡
Picture a clear image of the universe, undistorted by atmosphere.
ぎんが
わくせい
未知の銀河系や惑星系誕生の
秘密｡宇宙の物質進化｡➡
Unknown galaxies and solar systems waiting to be discovered.
The evolution of space.
しん
ただ美しい 深宇宙の鮮明な姿｡➡
And the vivid beauty of the universe.
一度でいいから見てみたい
惑星や小惑星の姿｡
A chance to see asteroids and meteorites up close.
はる
我々 天文学者には 遥か遠くまで
行く力はありませんが➡
As astronomers, we lack the ability to travel vast distances.
遥か遠くを見る力なら
我々に勝る者はいません｡
But we can see farther than anyone else.
きっと実現できます｡
ここにいる みんなの力があれば｡
I'm sure this telescope can work
if everyone in this room helps.
Houston Ellington Airport
(教官)このチャートには
航空路空域境界…｡
This chart shows the...
Too complicated.
こうほ
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生
アスキャンは➡
We astronaut candidates, or AsCans,
have come to Ellington Airport, near Johnson Space Center.
ジョンソン宇宙センターの
近くにある➡
エリントンフィールド空港に
来ている＞
To become an astronaut,
＜宇宙飛行士に
にんてい
認定されるためには➡
you must be licensed to pilot a T-38 jet.
さんじゅうはち
ジェット機Ｔ－３８の
そうじゅうしかく
操縦資格が必要なのだ＞
＜航空力学に始まり➡
Aerodynamics, engine system mechanics,
エンジンシステムなどの
メカニック➡
こうほう
基本的な航法に各種飛行ルール＞
basic flight navigation and rules...
＜覚えることは山ほどある｡
だけど…＞
There's a lot to learn.
But...
くんれん
《私はこの訓練を
ずっと 心待ちにしていた》
I've waited a long time for this training.
《あの日の日々人のように
私も人生初の➡
Finally, I'll get to experience the same thing Hibito did,
マッハを…体験…できるのだ｡➡
by breaking the sound barrier...
マッハ…マッハッハ…ハッハ》
Sound barrier...
S-Sound barrier...
《マッホ…》
ムッ君 なんかつらそうだね｡
寝てないの？
Mu, you look tired...
You didn't get any sleep?
No, no... Of course not.
まさかっ｡
《そう…寝てない》
No, I didn't get any sleep.
《昨日のアマンティの言葉が
気になって 全然眠れなかった》
I was up all night, thinking about what Amanti told me.
⦅誰かが…重い病気になる⦆
Someone will soon be stricken by serious illness.
《誰のことだ…》
Who did she mean?
ふあ～｡
きゅうけい
ふう…やっと休憩だよ｡
We finally have a break.
今 大丈夫だよ｡
Hello?
Sure, now is fine.
元気 元気｡
シャロンおばちゃんこそ元気？
I'm doing well...
How about you, Aunt Sharon?
Did he just say "Aunt Sharon"?
《ｼｬﾛﾝおばちゃんって言った今!?
ｼｬﾛﾝおばちゃんって言った今!?》
Did he just say "Aunt Sharon"?!
ど～したの セリカ｡
What's wrong, Serika?
《うわぁ～！》
Yeah.
さんぱち
そう 今日からＴ－３８の｡
We start training for the T-38 today.
Yes, it's a real jet.
そう すごいジェット機だよ｡
マッハだよ マッハ｡
It's supersonic!
まだ乗ってないけど｡
But I haven't been in one yet.
えっ こっち来てるの!?
《えっ こっち来てるの!?》
Huh? You're in the States?
What? She's in the States?!
Ah, you went to Goddard.
そうか ゴダードに！
あ…ちょっと待ってて｡
Oh, hold on...
今おばちゃんのすげぇファンのコが
すぐ近くにいるから➡
I'm with a big fan of yours right now.
ちょっと かわるね｡
I'll put her on.
Eh?
ムリです ムリです｡
No, no, no, no!
I can't do it... I can't do it.
大丈夫だよ｡シャロンは
せりかさんのこと知ってるよ｡
It's fine...
Sharon knows who you are.
Ah, hello... It's nice to meet you.
あ もしもし はじめまして
伊東せりかと申します｡
My name is Itou Serika.
はいっ いえいえ
こちらこそ｡
Yes.
No, the pleasure is mine!
《そこまで ファンとは…》
I didn't realize she was this big a fan.
昔 父がシャロンさんの本を
買ってくれて➡
My father bought me one of your books.
はい それ以来ずっと読んでます｡
Yes, I've read it so many times!
ありがとう！あなたにも
会ってみたいと思ってたのよ｡
Thank you.
I've been wanting to meet you.
ムッタから色々きいててね｡
Mutta's told me so much about you.
Oh? Are you serious?!
え～ そうなんですか～!?
《シャロン…》
Sharon...
C-Could it be Sharon who...
《まさか シャロンが…!?》
《い…いやそれはないだろ｡
元気な声してたし》
N-No, that can't be right.
She sounded perfectly fine.
ありがとうございます｡
南波さん｡
Thank you very much,
Nanba.
あ いやいや｡あ もしもし｡
Don't worry about it...
Ah, hello?
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ガッ！ガタッ！)
もしもし!?シャロンおばちゃん！
ちょっと！
Hello? Aunt Sharon?
Hey!
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ガタ)
Oh, I'm sorry! I dropped my phone...
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ｼｬﾛﾝ)
あ～ ごめんなさい｡
ケータイ 落としちゃった｡
あ…そう｡
Oh, really...
《ふ～ なんだビビッたぜ》
Man, that really scared me.
あさって
それじゃ 明後日には
ヒューストンに行くから｡
In two days, we'll be in Houston.
ええ またね｡
Yes, I'll see you then.
ん～ また落としちゃった｡
I dropped my phone again.
最近よくモノを落とすなぁ｡
These days, I keep dropping things...
I wonder if I damaged my phone.
こわ
ケータイ 壊れてないかな｡
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#63 Young Excitement
Will someone really get sick?
＜ホントに誰か病気になんのか!?
それが気になる中➡
With that over my head, I have to work hard at my training.
私は
訓練に備えた猛勉強に突入する＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Young Excitement"
You should go to the hospital again in the morning.
＜明日 朝から もう一度
病院へ行きましょう＞
＜私も同行します＞
I'll accompany you.
はし
まえ
走り出せ前向いて
そら
かじかむ手で空に描いた
きみ
みらい
しゅくふく
あか
君の未来に祝福の灯りともす
ひら
切り開け
その手で
こえ
聞こえてるかい？
この声が